# **MUHAMMED ANAS**

## MERN STACK DEVELOPER

+91 9747519239 | muhammedanasea2000@gmail.com | LinkedIn | GitHub | Portfolio | LeetCode

## **PROFILE SUMMARY**

Self-taught **MERN** stack developer driven by curiosity and commitment to creating innovative web applications. The journey as a developer has been driven by insatiable and a strong desire to create meaningful and innovative web applications. Self-learning skills allow for quick absorption and application of new technologies, making adaptability to the ever-evolving tech industry possible.

#### **EXPERIENCE**

FREELANCE March 2024 - Present

Full Stack Developer (MERN)

Specializing in end-to-end web application development using the MERN stack. Design and build responsive, scalable solutions for clients across industries, ensuring alignment with their unique business goals. Partner closely with stakeholders to transform requirements into user-centric applications, prioritizing performance and seamless functionality.

BOOTCAMP January 2023 - February 2024

Full Stack Developer (MERN)

During my internship at Brototype, I gained hands-on experience in building full-stack web applications using the MERN stack. I actively participated in weekly technical reviews with industry experts, which helped me refine my coding practices and contributed to a 20% improvement in overall project quality. Working in a collaborative, feedback-driven environment, I also enhanced my communication and teamwork skills, preparing me to thrive in dynamic development teams.

#### TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming Languages: JavaScript, HTML, CSS

Libraries and Framework: Node.js, Express.js, React.js, Next.js, Redux, Bootstrap, Tailwind CSS, Socket.io, JWT,

AJAX, EJS, TypeScript

Database: MongoDB, PostgreSQL, Firebase

Deployment: AWS EC2, Nginx, AWS Route53, Hostinger, Cloudinary, Vercel, Netlify, Render

Dev Tools: Git, GitHub, Postman, Figma, MongoDB Compass, Code Planner

Familiar with: Data structures and algorithms, Multer, Stripe, Puppeteer, Razorpay, REST API, MVC Architecture

## **PROJECTS**

#### **TRAVELLO**

Resort Booking Management Website

GitHub

Travello is an online platform designed specifically for booking resort accommodations. Its offering travelers streamlined access to a wide range of options with intuitive reservation processes and seamless navigation.

- Crafted an intuitive interface leveraging **React.js**, **Tailwind CSS** and **Node.js** for seamless navigation.
- Nodemailer is used to verify users and send notifications to property owners for authentication purposes.
- The user has a secure authentication and authorization system created using **JWT** tokens and it also includes easy login using **Google Auth**.

- Users can easily chat with property owners, which helps them understand more about the property. **Socket.io** enables a real-time chat experience between the user and the property owner.
- Integrated a **Stripe** payment option for users, enabling a secure online payment experience.

## **Ebiycle**

*E-commerce Website Live* | *GitHub* 

Ebiycle is an online e-commerce platform selling bicycles. Users can create an account and also track their orders.

- Developed an e-commerce platform using **Node.js**, **Express.js** and **MongoDB** following the **MVC** (Model-View-Controller) architecture for organized development.
- Integrated core features such as a product catalog, shopping cart, payment gateway, user reviews, order tracking and wishlists to elevate the shopping experience for cycling enthusiasts.
- Implemented robust user authentication and access control mechanisms utilizing **session**-based authentication, emphasizing data security and confidentiality.
- Handle media files by using **Cloudinary** for storing images and **Multer** for uploading files efficiently.
- Crafted an intuitive and visually appealing user interface with **CSS** and **Bootstrap**, ensuring seamless navigation and engagement for visitors interested in cycling products.
- Deployed the cycling e-commerce platform on AWS EC2 with Nginx, AWS Route53 and Certbot to guarantee optimal availability, scalability and security.

### **EDUCATION**

Bachelor of Computer Application
Kannur University
Higher Secondary(Biology Science)
GHSS Thariode, Wayanad

2018 - 2021 (Ongoing)

2016 - 2018